<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumph of a good conscience. Or a sermon preached upon the 2. of the Revel. the latter part of the 10 verse. VVherein the nature of faithfulnesse is in part opened, and the doctrine of perseverance confirmed, and some cases of conscience cleared. / By Paul Amiraut, minister of the Gospel at East Dearham, in the county of Norfolk.</title>
            <author>Amyraut, Paul, b. 1600 or 1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E426_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864047</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116266</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75308)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116266)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 67:E426[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumph of a good conscience. Or a sermon preached upon the 2. of the Revel. the latter part of the 10 verse. VVherein the nature of faithfulnesse is in part opened, and the doctrine of perseverance confirmed, and some cases of conscience cleared. / By Paul Amiraut, minister of the Gospel at East Dearham, in the county of Norfolk.</title>
                  <author>Amyraut, Paul, b. 1600 or 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Paine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 9th", "1647"; the 8 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation II, 10 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116266:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Triumph of a good Conſcience. OR A SERMON Preached upon the 2. of the <hi>Revel.</hi> the latter part of the 10 verſe.</p>
            <p>Wherein the nature of Faithfulneſſe is in part opened, and the doctrine of perſeverance confirmed, and ſome caſes of Conſcience cleared.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Paul Amiraut,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Eaſt Dearham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 25.23.</hi>
                  </bibl> Well done good and profitable ſervant, thou haſt been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things, enter thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ioy of thy Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Auguſtin.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Quod minimum minimum eſt, ſed in minimo fidelem eſſe magnum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Homerus.</bibl>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Paine.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116266:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116266:2"/>
            <head>To my worthy eſteemed friend Mr. <hi>Laurence Brinley,</hi> Citizen and Merchant of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot performe ſo much as I promiſed, but by performing more. I undertook upon your requeſt to preſent you a Copie of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in writing, and accordingly I ſet pen to paper, but my great diſtractions came ſo faſt upon me, that in ſtead of writing <hi>I</hi> fell to ſcribling, ſo that if J had offered you my written copie, J ſhould have exhibited un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you unknown myſteries in the letter, though <hi>I</hi> ſpeake but plain things for the matter. So that <hi>I</hi> ſaw, <hi>I</hi> could not make this Sermon fit for private vſe, but by expoſing it to publique view. And ſo lodging in a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters houſe, I did addreſſe my ſelfe to the preſſe, and that which others make their choice, <hi>I</hi> made my refuge, therefore if any blame me for ſitting in the Printers ſtocke, let him take this for an Apologie. And ſince <hi>I</hi> am caſt into this <hi>dilemma,</hi> that either <hi>I</hi> muſt be a fool in print, or be guilty of the breach of promiſe, let the moſt cenſorious criticks know, that <hi>I</hi> eſteem that follie wiſedome, that doth exempt me from the guilt of unfaithfullneſſe, which in this ſhort diſcourſe <hi>I</hi> have ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized
<pb facs="tcp:116266:3"/> with the black brand of Hell. But if there be no remedie, but this ſhort treatiſe muſt be marked out for cenſure and reproach, <hi>I</hi> paſſe not for it, for it ſhall run but the ſame fate with the Author, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for no other cauſe, but for that <hi>I</hi> deſire to be acquainted with the ſubiect <hi>I</hi> treat of: And truly <hi>I</hi> expect to have this Sermon cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſome for the Authors ſake, and by others <hi>I</hi> expect to have the Author cenſured for the Sermons ſake. However <hi>I</hi> deſire to be no worſe dealt witha, l then <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple was by <hi>Nebuzardan,</hi> who though he deſtroyed it, yet he took the gold. So if men will but own the ſubiect of this Sermon, and realize it in their practice, let them make me an Anatomie of reproach. <hi>I</hi> have prepared my back and ſhoulders to beare it. But as for you worthy Sir, <hi>I</hi> doubt not, but you will owne this diſcourſe with all faults, ſince you have ſo often urged me to own my promiſe, and <hi>I</hi> am glad it ſhall lodge in the boſome of him, who in theſe ſtaggering and declining times, hath made his breſt the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie of this grace of faithfullneſſe, in adhering to Goſpell principles, which will be your Crown, and your reioycing in the day of the Lord Ieſus, in whoſe hand <hi>I</hi> leave you, who will be your <hi>Iacin</hi> and your <hi>Boaz,</hi> your ſtrength and eſtabliſhment, reſting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all Goſpel ſervices,</hi> Paul Amiraut.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:116266:3"/>
            <head>The Triumph of a good Conſcience &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Reve. chap. 2. ver. 10</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Be thou faithfull unto the death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a good ſaying of an ancient writer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his ſpeech to godly Chriſtians, <hi>Feare not O faithful ſoule, thoſe outward evills which thou ſhalt ſuffer, for thy keeper ſleepeth not, which preſerveth thee: But be afraid of ſinne and inward evills, for thy keeper ſleepeth not, which obſerveth thee.</hi> So in this verſe the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> is bidden not to feare thoſe outward evils which ſhe ſhould ſuffer, though the Divel ſhould caſt ſome of them into priſon &amp;c. but here in my text, ſhe is bidden implicitly to feare the inward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of Apoſtacie, and explicitly exhorted unto perſeverance. <hi>Be thou faithfull unto the death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words naturally branch themſelves into two parts, a precept and a promiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The precept, <hi>Be thou faithfull unto death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The promiſe, <hi>and</hi> I <hi>ſhal give thee a Crown of life.</hi> But I ſhal only ſpeak ſomthing of the firſt.</p>
            <p>The thing that is now to be explained, is the word faithfull, which though it admit of an ample deſcription, &amp; takes in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ingredients, yet being confined to the ſtraights of time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſevere moderator of theſe exerciſes, I ſhal only open the main thing that denominates a man to be faithfull; and that is the covenant keeping grace, wherby a man keeps touch with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116266:4"/> God in performing thoſe vowes and promiſes, he hath made unto him, in the 6. of <hi>Hoſea</hi> verſe the 7. <hi>They like men have tranſgreſſed the Covenant, they have dealt treacherouſly againſt me:</hi> to tranſgres the covenant is made there an act of treachery, &amp; unfaithfulneſſe, therefore by the Law of contraries, to keepe the covenant is an act of faithfulneſſe: it is the ſame with obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in regard of the matter, but it differs from it in regard of the manner,<note place="margin">☞</note> for obedience hath relation to the command, as it is Gods word, but faithfulneſſe hath relation to the command, as we have made it ours, by entring into Covenant and promiſe to performe it: Now a faithfull Chriſtian often breakes Gods word, but never goes ſo far, as to break his own, as ſhal be made good in the proſecution of this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Theſe things premiſed, the point of obſervation which I ſhall hold forth unto you at this time, is this: That <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> if it be of the right Stamp wil hold out unto death. For confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof, take a view of theſe Scriptures, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Iob</hi> 27. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. Theſe Scriptures ſhew the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the doctrine, proving that it is ſo, and now we ſhall produce reaſons to ſhew the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the doctrine, and to give an account that it is ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Reaſon"/> The 1. Reaſon is taken from the excellency of this grace of faithfulneſſe, for faithfulneſſe is the higheſt perfection a Chriſtian can attain unto in this life, there will ever ſomthing be wanting even in the beſt in point of obedience, which cannot be made up but in the truth and ſoundneſſe thereof: hence it is that where the ſcriptures ſpeak of perfection, it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſincerity, in the feeling and acknowledgement of our imperfection, ioyned with a conſtant endeavour after perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.14.15. ſo the 1 of <hi>Chron.</hi> the 12. they that in the 33. are ſaid not to be of a double heart are ſaid in the 38. verſe to be of a perfect heart. Now faithfullneſſe is therefore called perfection, becauſe thoſe that are faithful, are furniſhed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116266:4"/> with ſuch things as accompany ſalvation, and they that are ſuch cannot fall away, but muſt needes ſtand compleat in all the will of God. In the 6. of the <hi>Heb.</hi> the 5. and 8. verſes you may reade of ſome that went very far, and yet the Apoſtle ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that they might fall away, but in the 9. verſe he is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perſwaded of the faithfull Hebrewes, becauſe they were furniſh'd with ſuch things as did accompany ſalvation: they had ſuch gifts, as would not leave them halfe way to heaven, as <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> left her mother in Law <hi>Naomi,</hi> but would ſtick to them, till they were houſed in the bleſſed manſions of eternity; ſo that all Apoſtates and Retrogades, and all thoſe that are turned the Devils proſelytes, caſting off their faith, to make up their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, have notwitſtanding their glittering ſhewes, and dazeling excellencies, wanted thoſe things that accompany ſalvation, which a faithfull Chriſtan, and one that hath attained to a true Evangelicall perfection cannot be without.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Faithfulneſſe is a grace that admits of no corrupting, and Apoſtatizing principles, it is like the <hi>Maronaan</hi> wine,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> which though it be mingled with other liquour, and drinkes, yet it keepes its ſweetneſſe and its ſtrength, without any abatement. Faithfull men in Scripture are deſcribed by this, that they have renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. ſhewing that there is no root nor principle of Apoſtacy to be found in ſuch, now if there be no hidden root of apoſtacy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, there can never be any appearance of Apoſtacy without. But that place of <hi>Iſay</hi> is very full chap. 11. ver. 5. where faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe is called the girdle of the reines, it is called a girdle,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> becauſe as a girdle tyes our clothes faſt unto us, that they may not hang looſe; ſo a faithfull Chriſtian girds the commands of God cloſe about his Soule, to prevent all looſeneſſe, and Libertiniſme in his life and converſation, and it is called the girdle of the reines, becauſe, as the reines, in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116266:5"/> bodie purge out the bad blood, that it may not infect the liver, ſo faithfulneſſe, though it cannot prevent all ſin, yet it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually purging of it, that it may not infect the heart, and by that meanes theſe hidden things of diſhoneſty are kept out, which might engage us to Apoſtacy and falling away, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. ver. 23. It is impoſſible to poyſon the Sea, becauſe the Sea doth ever work out what ever is offenſive unto it.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> So it is impoſſible that a faithfull man ſhould be corrupted, becauſe faithfulneſſe doth alwayes purge out what ever is deſtructive unto it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. Faithfullneſſe is under the protection of never failing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: The Lord promiſes that faithfull perſons ſhall be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable as mount Zion. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>They are as an houſe builded upon the Rock, which no windes or waves are able to overturne. Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>Choſen ones, whom it is impoſsible for to ſeduce Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>They are Chriſts ſheepe, whom no man ſhall pluck out of his Fathers hand. Iohn</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>They are kept by the power of God to ſalvation.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Though they fall they ſhall not be caſt away: for the Lord holdeth them up with his hand,.</hi> Surely it is impoſſible that a people of ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſhould periſh, yes ſay ſome, for they may unpeople them ſelves by ſinne, and the Lord may unpromiſe them in a way of judgement:<note place="margin">Simile.</note> Not ſo ſay I, for the promiſes not only prepare ſalvation for us, but prepare us for ſalvation too in a way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and obedience: ſee <hi>Jeremy,</hi> 31. ver. 32. and 32. ver. 40. like ſome trades-men that do not only doe thoſe workes that belong to their trade, but frame and faſhion thoſe very tooles, by which they work: ſo here not only happineſſe, but holineſſe, (which is the toole by which it is wrought) flowes from the belly of the promiſe. So much by way of confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Vſe.</head>
               <p>Here I might ſay ſome thing by way of Confutation, for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116266:5"/> this truth meets with much contradiction abroad, of thoſe that deny perſeverance to be eſſentiall to this grace of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe: and allow of no other perſeverance, but that which comes by hap-hazard, affirming that Gods faithfull ones may fall into ſuch ſinnes, as may cauſe an utter extinction of grace in them. But I ſhall have ſome thing to ſay to theſe anon, in anſwer to an objection.</p>
               <p>For the preſent, obſerve what a glorious change Chriſt hath wrought in death.</p>
               <p>For in it ſelfe, it is the prologue and preface and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that dolefull and fiery tragedie, which ſhall be acted in hell, but here in my text it is the <hi>non ultra,</hi> the <hi>Hercules Pillar,</hi> and the end of all the labours, and ſufferings of the Saints of God here upon earth. There is no more required of them but to lengthen out their active and paſſive obedience to the houre of death, then their race is at an end, and their endleſſe happineſſe takes place. In it ſelfe it is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe woes, that ſhall perſevere unto all eternity. But here in my text it is the <hi>Colophon:</hi> the laſt draught, and the Crowne of that perſeverance, that muſt help us to a Crowne of life. Which may miniſter abundance of comfort to faithfull Chriſtians in theſe ſtormy and tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times: We have ſeen of late the King of terrors ride abroad in triumph, and death enter in at our windowes in a ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous fierie attire, and we may plainly perceive that the fiery Comet ſtill hangs over our heads, our ſinnes and diſtractions ſtill ſolliciting God to trade with us in a bargaine of blood: Now theſe that know not what change Chriſt hath wrought in death, may be filled with terror, to ſee the <hi>Cypreſſe</hi> tree planted before their dores. But faithfull Chriſtians have no cauſe to feare death: For why ſhould they be afraid of that, which puts an end to all their labours and ſufferings, that ſtrips them of their ragges, to cloth them with robes, that brings
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116266:6"/> them glad tidings of the conſumption of their ſinnes and of the conſummation of their graces, ſetting a garland of glory, upon their heads w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> will not wither unto all eternity.</p>
               <p>Ob. But ſome will ſay, we feare not much a naturall death, ſuch a death, as cauſeth a faire diſſolution by the mutiny of Malignant humors from within, but it is terrible to have our earthly Tabernacle pull'd downe violently by Malignant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from without, and to be tormented to death in a way of cruelty by brutiſh men skillfull to deſtroy. I anſwer that if faithfull Chriſtians knew their ſtrength, and did well underſtand their priviledges, they would as cheerefully upon Chriſts call open their boſomes to a violent death, as to a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death: for this is the death that Chriſt calls a Baptiſme. <hi>Matt.</hi> 20.23. Now Baptiſme ſhould not be grievous to a Chriſtian,<note place="margin">☞</note> ſeeing it is a ſigne and ſeale of the Covenant, no more ſhould any perſecution and Martyrdome inflicted for the cauſe of Chriſt, be grievous unto us, for the experience of Gods love ever runnes in that channell. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4. Hence it is remarkable, that both under the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there were but two Sacraments, and the firſt of theſe is a kinde of an afflicting Sacrament, as Circumciſion in the one, which drew blood, and cauſed much ſmart, and paine and ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the bodie, though indeed the Paſſeover was a meere refreſhing Sacrament.</p>
               <p>So Baptiſme is ſomewhat afflicting too, eſpecially in the Eaſtern parts and hot climats of the world, where the partie baptized was dipp'd over head and ears in water, though the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is a meere refreſhing Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance:<note place="margin">☞</note> but this ſhewes that God convayes the ſenſe of his love as well in a way of affliction, as in a way of conſolation, and this I deſire may be obſerved; That as ſome afflictions are Sacraments, ſo all afflictions are Sacramentall to beleevers. Therefore let it never trouble us if we be expoſed to perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116266:6"/> or Martyrdome, ſo long as we can match a good heart to a good cauſe. For as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith well, though death in it ſelfe be the puniſhment of ſinne, it is now through the wonderfull power of Chriſt made an inlet unto glory. To ſuffer for Chriſt ſaith <hi>Bradford,</hi> is to goe to Heaven on horſeback. And the ſame <hi>Auſtin</hi> further ſhewing the difference of that death,<note place="margin">☜</note> that is now impoſed upon Martyrs from that death, which was firſt threatned upon man in paradice, doth ſweetly runne upon this deſcant: Once it was ſaid unto man, if thou ſinneſt thou ſhalt die, but now it is ſaid to the Martyr, if thou doſt not die, thou ſhalt ſinne: then it was ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, if thou breakeſt the Commandement thou ſhalt die the death, but now it is ſaid to the Martyr, if thou refuſeſt to ſuffer death for a good cauſe, thou ſhalt break the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That which was once a matter of terror, to affright men from ſinning at all, is now the matter of our comfort, becauſe it tranſlates us into ſuch an eſtate, where we ſhall ſinne no more. Then death came in by ſinning: But now holineſſe is perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by dying. <hi>Ob.</hi> But it will be ſaid, that thoſe things are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the fleſh, and therefore it is an hard matter willingly to ſtoope to ſuch hot ſervices. I anſwer.</p>
               <p>Bee it ſo, yet there is enough in the grace of faithfulneſſe to carrie us through: This grace will make us ready, and therefore called the girdle of the ſoule, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.14. Now when a man hath once put on his girdle, he hath then made himſelf readie for his worke. Hence the latin, <hi>accingi ad opus,</hi> and that of Chriſt, <hi>Gird up the loynes of your mindes,</hi> are expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons importing a readineſſe to goe about our taske. Now when once a man hath made himſelfe readie for a buſineſſe, though very harſh &amp; unpleaſing in it ſelf; yet when his ſpirit is leaven'd and rayſed, and ſo a ſutableneſſe wrought betwixt it, and his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, then the maine ſtreame of his deſires and affection is carried after it, and it would be a trouble and vexation unto him to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116266:7"/> taken of from it. See this in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 21. v. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Being diſſwaded from going up to <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> by many of the Saints, becauſe they underſtood, by the Prophet <hi>Agabus</hi> the hard meaſure, that he ſhould meet withall there, he grew into ſome paſſion, and ſet himſelfe with might and maine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt this temptation of the right hand, wherwith he was aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaying, <hi>what meane you to weepe and breake my heart, for I am readie not to be bound onely, but alſo to die at Hieruſalem for the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, will you take me of from that buſineſſe, that I have made my ſelfe readie for? O this is a bitter vexation to me, and if you had deviſed how to grieve my ſpirit, you could hardly have done it to better purpoſe, then by aſſaulting me with ſuch a tentation: ſince therefore this is the property of faithfulneſſe to make us ready for any ſervice that Chriſt ſhall expoſe us unto, feare not the weakneſſe of the fleſh to graſple with a ſuffering condition, for faithfulneſſe will put ſugar enough into the bittereſt cup, to make it ſweet and pleaſant unto thy taſt. Indeed if thou beeſt unſound and unfaithfull, ſuch times as theſe may ſpeak terror unto thee.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> An unſound legge will ake in a ſtorme, and an evill conſcience wil ake in ſhaking times, in the 33. <hi>Eſa. v.</hi> 14. <hi>The ſinners of Sion are afraid, Fearefulneſſe hath ſurprized the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits, who among us ſhall dwel with the devouring fire? who among us ſhal dwell with everlaſting burnings?</hi> Why, whats the matter? The things threatned in that chapter, were temporall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the leſſer furniture of mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> and yet behold they cry out of eternall judgements, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the full weight of mount <hi>Ebal</hi> was ready to fall upon them? what ſhould be the reaſon of it, ſurely it lyes in this, that when God ſends temporal judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">☞</note> a bad conſcience wil ſtep in, and eeke out the judgements by ſtretching them upon the tenter hookes of eternity, that is, whilſt we are afflicted with the ſenſe of the preſent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a bad conſcience will then beſtirre it ſelfe, and let us ſee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116266:7"/> the ſucceſſion of thoſe woes, which ſhall continue in hell for ever, and whileſt we are delivered to the hand-killing, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will deliver us to the hand writing, and this will miniſter cauſe enough for ſuch an Out-cry. <hi>Who among us. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the righteous may be as bold as a Lyon, Prov.</hi> 28. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being aſſured by Gods word which cannot lye, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 37. that in all theſe things he ſhall be more then a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,<note place="margin">☜</note> through Chriſt that loved him. We reade of two ſorts of conquerours in the 11. of the <hi>Heb.</hi> from the 33. verſe &amp;c. one that conquered in a way of violence, and theſe were but conquerours, an other ſort from the 37. ver. &amp;c. who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered in a way of patience, and theſe though they ſeemed to be but a ragged regiment in compariſon of the former, yet <hi>they were not only conquerours, but more then conquerours,</hi> becauſe they gave great odds, (to wit) their lives, eſtates, liberty, eaſe, &amp;c. and yet conquered. Therefore let faithful Chriſtians com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another with ſuch things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> I but ſome poore ſouls wil ſay, true theſe are great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, but they belong only to ſuch as are faithfull, but I feare I am not faithfull: therefore I dare not peepe into this Arke, nor houſe my ſelf in this Rock. This Objection makes a bridge to cary us over to an uſe of examination.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Vſe of Examination.</head>
               <p>And therefore, that we may come to that uſe, I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this feare of thine is no bad ſigne, if other things be anſwerable, for faithfulneſſe is a ſelf-ſuſpecting grace: Wee ſee in the 26. of <hi>Mat.</hi> the 22. ver. when our Saviour Chriſt told his Diſciples that one of them ſhould betray him, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Diſciples, and thoſe that were cleare from hatching ſuch a damnable plot, ſuſpected themſelves firſt, as appeares by that queſtion they propounded to Chriſt, <hi>Maſter is it</hi> I <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Judas</hi> which was the Traytor indeed did lagg behind, and would not ſeeme to ſuſpect himſelfe till for ſhame he could not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116266:8"/> hold out no longer, and then he comes in faintly and propounds the ſame queſtion that the reſt did ver. 25. <hi>Maſter is it</hi> I, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art not any whit the leſſe faithfull, for ſuſpecting thy unfaithfullneſſe.</p>
               <p>But becauſe a baſe diſſembling Hypocrite may come in though limping and make a ſhew of ſelf-ſuſpicion, therefore a faithful Chriſtian in this outſtrips an unſound and fork'd tongu'd hypocrite, that he doth not only ſuſpect himſelfe, but he deſireth to be throughly ſearched and ranſackd to the bottome <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. verſe 1.2. This is the meere, and the doole ſtone that parts the ſincere Chriſtian and the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> For unſound hearts as unſound leggs deſire to be hid; and though they may ſubmit to ſome kinde of ſearch and examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet it is with them as it was with <hi>Rachel,</hi> when her Father <hi>Laban</hi> came to ſearch for his Idols in her tents, ſhe had laid the Idols under her, and ſat upon them, and though ſhe gave him leave to ſearch in her tent, yet when he offered to ſearch under her, where the Idols were, ſhe told him ſhe could not ſit up, <hi>becauſe it was with her after the manner of Women.</hi> So in Hypocrites there is ever ſomething, which is either erroneous in their judgment, or vicious in their practiſe which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not indure ſhould be ranſacked, let a man ſearch there, and they will tell you, that they are are as other men are, and ſo with the Harlot <hi>they wipe their mouth,</hi> and ſay they <hi>have committed no iniquity.</hi> But an upright Chriſtian like a faithfull Steward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth, when the day of Audit comes, he is content God ſhall reckon with him like an <hi>enemy,</hi> but he reſolves to pay like a <hi>friend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet the tryall of faithfullneſſe is very ſtrict, a man that will be conſcience proofe in this tryall muſt arme himſelfe to give a ſtrict account for ſmall things, as well as for great, when wee try our ſervants for their worke, we try them in great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but when we try them for their truth we try them in ſmal
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116266:8"/> matters, if we finde them purloyning but a ſmall peece of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, we conclude preſently, that they that are unfaithfull in ſo ſmall a thing, would likewiſe prove unfaithfull in a greater; ſo they that deſpiſe any of Gods wayes, or allow themſelves in the practiſe of any ſinne, though never ſo ſmall, crack their credit in point of faithfullneſſe, according to that of <hi>Luke</hi> 16. v. 10. <hi>He that is faithfull in the leaſt, he is all ſo faitfull in much, and he that is unjuſt in the leaſt, is unjuſt alſo in much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But ſome will ſay, ſhall every little ſinne foil us, in this Tryall, and give us the Denomination of unfaithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>I anſwer that in this tryall we muſt nor make uſe of a paire of Compaſſe to examine the <hi>quantity</hi> of the offence, but of a touch-ſtone to examine the <hi>quality</hi> of the offence. The leaſt quantity of leaven, is able to turne a Paſſeover into pollution, ſo the leaſt ſinne defiles us, if it be an act of unfaithfullneſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwayes ſinne though it be great in regard of the bulke; will not pollute us, if there be not a tang of unfaithfullneſſe in it.</p>
               <p>Now then to joyne iſſue with mens hearts and conſcences, you muſt remember, what I told you in the deſcription of this grace, that faithfullneſſe <hi>is to keepe touch with God in performing our Covenant,</hi> therefore if the ſinne be of that nature, as that thou haſt brooke the Covenant, the leproſie, ſticks to thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and thou art uncleane, but if the Covenant be not broken by thy ſinne, it is no fretting leproſie what ever the ſinne be, and after thou haſt bin ſhut up a while in the Cloſet of repentance, and godly ſorrow, thou wilt cleare thy ſelfe as a fountain doth, that caſts out her mudd. 2. <hi>cor.</hi> chap. 7. ver. 11. <hi>For behold this ſelfe ſame thing, that yee ſorrowed after a good ſort, what care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe it wrought in you; yea, what clearing of your ſelves; yea, what indignation; yea, what feare; yea, what vehement deſire; yea, what zeale; yea, what revenge: in all things yee have approved
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116266:9"/> your ſelves to be clear in this matter.</hi> It is true every ſinne in it ſelfe is a breath of the Covenant. But every man breakes not the Covenant, by committing of ſinne. Circumſtances may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the nature of ſinne, ſo that a ſinne being clothed with theſe Circumſtances, ſhall be no breach of the Covenant, though in a <hi>Mathematicall conſideration,</hi> abſtracted from ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, it would certainly prove ſo. Know therefore, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Covenants are not broken by ſinnes of infirmitie, but onely by ſinnes of preſumption. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12, 13. There are two ſorts of ſinnes mentioned: Some which <hi>David</hi> deſires might be pardoned, and thoſe are his ſecret ſinnes, or ſinnes of infirmitie: Others that <hi>David</hi> deſires to be kept from, and thoſe are preſumptuous ſinnes, and he gives this as a reaſon, that if they ſhould prevaile, he ſhould be guilty of that great offence, which is no other, but the breach of the Covenant. A man is not counted a promiſe breaker, that is diſabled by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or weakneſſe to break his word,<note place="margin">Simele.</note> but he that is ſet a worke by ſome hidden principle of diſhoneſtie to violate his promiſe, So infirmities are in the nature of ſoule ſickneſſes, they are ſins turned into diſeaſes, therefore they pronounce not a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull: But preſumptuous ſins are the fruits of corrupt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and theſe defile us. Now that you may know the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt theſe, I will make uſe of a Scripture alluſion, which (as I ſuppoſe) will be of much uſe to facilitate this point for your underſtanding and judgement.</p>
               <p>In the 9th. of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> you read there the ſtory of the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites.</hi> And we find that they were a parcell of thoſe accurſed nations, which by Gods ſpeciall command were devoted to deſtruction. Yet notwithſtanding, by a trick they had they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped. So ſinnes of infirmitie are a parcell of that accurſed maſſe of ſin, which ought to be deſtroyed and cut off by morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. But yet they are ſuch ſinnes as doe eſcape many times.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116266:9"/> So that a Chriſtian ſhall be troubled with them all his life long, but yet with the ſame ſucceſſe that the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> had, the ſame thing befalling their ſinnes, that befell the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As firſt, they had a meane office put upon them, they were made hewers of wood, and drawers of water. So ſinnes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie are ſinnes in office, and their office is to ſet the pump of godly ſorrow and humiliation agoing. This I confeſſe they doe as it were againſt the hare, and as the Apoſtle ſaith of the Creatures, that they are ſubject to vanity, <hi>not of their own will, but by reaſon of him, that hath ſubiected them in hope.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.20.</note> So with ſome alteration I may ſay, that theſe ſinnes execute not this office of themſelves, but by the power of God, who can work by contraries, and who hereby outſhoots the Divell in his own bow. For he found the way to draw <hi>pride</hi> out of Gods <hi>graces,</hi> and the Lord to requite him, will draw <hi>humiliation</hi> out of thoſe <hi>ſinnes,</hi> whereof he is the author. Thus he ſuffered <hi>Ezekiah</hi> to fall, that he might know what was in his heart, and ſo bee humbled. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.31.</p>
               <p>To open this a little further, I lay this for a ground, that Ieſus Chriſt might as eaſily have beſtowed perfect ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon us, the firſt moment of our converſion,<note place="margin">☜</note> as he doth then perfect juſtification. And whereas there are two things in ſinne, the <hi>guilt</hi> and the <hi>filth,</hi> whereof the one is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to us, the other is <hi>offenſive</hi> to God, it ſhould ſeem that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſanctification which removes the latter, ſhould rather have been wrought by Chriſt, then perfect juſtification, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves the former, becauſe Gods glory ought more to be ſought after, then mans good. Some great reaſons ſure there muſt be for this, among which I ſuppoſe this to be one of the chiefe. That Gods juſtice might ſtill keep a Court, as well as his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: which could not have been, if all ſinne had been aboliſhed.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116266:10"/> For where there is no tranſgreſſion, there can be no court of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice erected. Hence it is that all the prayers of the Saints, begin with confeſſions, and ſelf accuſations for ſinne, which are as ſo many arraignments in the Court of Gods juſtice, after which an appeale lyes faire in the Court of Gods mercy. Now had ſinne been quite aboliſhed, the Court of juſtice like <hi>Ianus</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the time of peace had been quite ſhut up. And God by granting a priviledge ſhould have extinguiſhed thoſe rents and revenues that come in to him by vertue of that Court. Which thoſe poore Publicans, theſe ſinnes of infirmitie bring in. So then thoſe ſinnes that are not as a prick in the fleſh to humble us, are no ſinnes of infirmitie, but ſinnes of preſumption.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> after their eſcape, complied not with thoſe nations whereof they were a parcell, but were rather a meanes to help to deſtroy them, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 10. So ſinnes of infirmity doe not uphold other ſinnes, but rather helpe to mortifie them. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> denyall of his maſter did wholly deſtroy his carnall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. So the meſſenger of <hi>Satan</hi> where with <hi>Paul</hi> was buffeted, being according to Interpreters, ſome luſt or other ſtirring with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, was a meanes to pull down that exaltation, which might have been occaſioned by thoſe divine raptures and revelations which he injoyed. There is never a ſin of infirmitie, but is a meanes to keep out a worſe ſin, into which the Saints of God would have falne, if they had not been troubled with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie. I appeale to the experiences of Chriſtians for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this truth. May not a Chriſtian ſay, O if I had not been troubled with a dead heart, I ſhould have been troubled with a proud heart. And let me mind you here of a ſtrange par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox, the more ſins of infirmitie a Chriſtian is troubled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the fewer ſinnes he hath. Miſtake me not, I doe not ſay, but that one that hath fewer ſinnes of infirmitie, is freer from ſinne, then he that hath more. But you may conceive my meaning by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116266:10"/> this Compariſon. The more ruines of houſes the fewer houſes, becauſe if theſe ruines were not, we ſhould have houſes built in their compleat fabrick. So the more ſinnes of infirmitie, the fewer ſinnes, becauſe if theſe infirmities were not, we ſhould have ſinne in its compleat poſture, and in its full perfection. whereas ſinnes of infirmitie are but the ruines or relikes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of ſinne.</p>
               <p>And I might add this, that the more ſinnes of infirmitie, the more graces, not but that a man that hath fewer of thoſe ſins hath more grace. But it is true in this ſenſe. A ſin of infirmitie is not a totall ſin, but a defect of the contrary grace ariſing from the imperfection of it. As pride in the Saints ir not a compleat pride, but is only a defect in their humilitie. So their unbeliefe is not a compleat unbeliefe, but it is only a weake and an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect faith, ſo that as we ſay of ſmoake, that it is contrary unto fire, yet it is a ſigne of fire, ſo may we ſay, that theſe ſins though contrary to grace, yet they are a ſigne of grace, for they are but a defect of it. And in this ſenſe we may ſay, that the more ſinnes of infirmitie, the more grace.</p>
               <p>Now ſinnes of preſumption are of another nature. They come within the compaſſe of the ſtatute of maintenance, they are ſo farre from pulling down other ſinnes, as they doe rather uphold them, one ſin of preſumption making way for another. Hence preſumptuous ſinners are ſaid to pul down ſin with cart-ropes, and iniquitie with cords of vanitie. <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.18. And <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> tells us, that preſumptuous ſinners ad drunkenſſe to thirſt, and rebellion to tranſgreſſion. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. As we ſay of the ſnow,<note place="margin">Simele.</note> that if it do not melt it lyes for more, ſo ſinnes of preſumption are ſinnes which melt not in a way of repentance, therefore they make way for other ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Againe ſinnes of preſumption are not meer defects of grace, but they are ſuch ſinnes as doe wholly exclude the contrary
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116266:11"/> grace, pride if it be a ſinne of infirmitie, wholly excludes humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> gave occaſion to the greateſt victory that ever was obtained. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10. A victory wherein the ſtarrs of heaven fought for them, and the Sun and Moon ſtood ſtill till they had avenged themſelves of their enemies, the like where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was never done before, nor likely to be hereafter. So ſinnes of infirmitie give us occaſion to judge our ſelves, which judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is after turned into a ſpirituall victory, <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.20. A victory exceeding great and glorious, wherein if the hoaſt of heaven did not fight for us,<note place="margin">☞</note> if the bleſſed Angels did not <hi>carrie us in their hands, that we might tread upon Dragons, and trample upon Scorpions,</hi> yea, if Chriſt the Sun of righteouſneſſe did not ſtand ſtill, and abide conſtant to us in his promiſes of ſupport and aſſiſtance. Yea, if he did not ſtay the Moone too, that is, our fickle and inconſtant hearts, that we might not wholly fall from him, O what would become of us. How ſoone would <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Cacus</hi> like draw us backward into his denn, and take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the biaſſe of our corruptions to rowle us into the bottomleſſe pit. For by this meanes <hi>Satan</hi> hath abundance of advantage over us, becauſe he hath a ſtrong partie &amp; faction in us. Grace as a reverend Divine hath obſerv'd, is but as a ſpark, and corruption as much ſmoake, and moiſture damping it. Grace is but as a Candle, and that in a ſocket among huge and boiſtrous winds. Therefore for God to bring forth judgement into <hi>victory,</hi> this is <hi>victory</hi> indeed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Enochs</hi> tranſlation profeſſeth, <hi>that he wonders at nothing ſo much as this,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                  <hi>that Enoch with a body of fleſh pasſing through the ayre, which is the Divells territory (and therfore he is called the Prince of the aire) yet he ſhould paſſe unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested, the Divell not throwing ſo much as a ſtone at the mud-wall of his body, though he was his greatest enemie at that time, even when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116266:11"/> he came joſſling by, and confronted him as it were in the place of his own dominion,</hi> So it is a thing that may carrie us to the higheſt pitch of admiration, to ſee a Chriſtian paſſe through the hoaſts of the Divells temptations, with not only a body of duſt, which he may feed upon as a Serpent. For <hi>duſt is the Serpents meat,</hi> but with a body of ſin too, which he may command as a Captain to fight under his helliſh ſtandard, and yet to Come forth as Chriſt did out of <hi>Bozrah,</hi> having his garment ſtained with the blood of his enemies, <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.17. &amp;c. His ſmall and ſcarce appearing grace being like unto <hi>Ionathans arrowes, which never returned emptie, from the blood of the ſlaine, and the fast of the mightie,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.22. This is worth an <hi>Io paan.</hi> and an <hi>Io tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amphe.</hi> Well may a Chriſtian ſay in this caſe with the Apoſtle. <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O Hell, where is thy victory? The ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the Law. But thankes be to God, who giveth us the victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56, 57.</p>
               <p>But ſinnes of preſumption doe not make way for ſuch victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but on the contrary, preſumptuous ſinners lye down at Satans feet as his bond ſlaves, they are ſaid to be overcome of ſinne, and to be taken Captives by Satan at his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>You therefore that pretend your ſinnes are ſinnes of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſee whether you can ſhew the trophees and monuments of ſuch ſpirituall victories as theſe are, elſe you have ſome cauſe to ſuſpect your ſelves. It will not be ſufficient in this caſe to alledge your forſaking of groſſe ſinnes, as drunkenneſſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, &amp;c. this doth not argue victory, for theſe ſinnes muſt not be ſubdued in a way of <hi>victory,</hi> but they muſt be eſcaped in a way of <hi>flight.</hi> And therefore you have that expreſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> concerning ſome Apoſtates, that had eſcaped the pollutions of the world, and afterwards proved guilty of a Relaps,<note place="margin">Simele.</note> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. If an houſe were much infected with the plague, though
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116266:12"/> they were enemies, an Armie of Soldiers would hardly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe it about, and lay ſledge to it to ſubdue it, but they would rather flie from it, and keep a diſtance from it. So ſuch infections and peſtiferous ſlnnes as theſe muſt be the obiect of our flight and not of our victories. Neither can we be ſaid to have eſcaped them, by refraining from thoſe ſinnes, unleſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we avoid thoſe occaſions and appearances of evill, that bring us neere them, becauſe they that flee from any thing; muſt not come as neere as they can, but muſt keep at as great a diſtance as they can. For men to refrain from drunkenneſſe, and yet fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low tipling, to profeſſe to hate pride, and yet delight in ſtrange apparell, to refraine from the act of uncleaneneſſe, and yet to practiſe dalliance, to abhorre Idolatry, and to obſerve ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ceremonies, is to come ſo neere thoſe groſſe ſinnes, as it cannot be ſaid of us, that we have eſcaped them. And yet when we have thus eſcaped them, we are not thereby in a capacitie to be crowned as ſpirituall Conquerors. For the Apoſtates ſpoken of in that place of <hi>Peter</hi> had gone thus farre, and yet afterwards made it appeare by their Apoſtacie, that they never knew what it is to conquer ſin.</p>
               <p>But the ſubduing of our ſpirituall corruptions, as our unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, our ſpirituall pride, vaine glory, love of the world, &amp;c. Theſe are the victories, wherby we muſt try our ſelves, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we find that our ſins have made a ſpiritual conqueſt of them it is to be feared our ſins are not ſins of infirmitie but ſins of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by reaſon of theſe <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> could the better intend their higher imployments, becauſe they did their drudgery worke for them, ſo whiles theſe ſins of infirmitie doe keep the ſoul low in a way of humiliation, and as it were help forward this ſubmiſſive worke, Chriſtians that by are the better inabled to walke ſtrictly and exactly in all the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116266:12"/> wayes of God. Thoſe that in the 7. of the <hi>Romans</hi> complain ſo much of the body of death, which they carrie about them in the perſon of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> are ſuch as <hi>walke not according to to the fleſh, but according to the ſpirit. Rom.</hi> 8.1. If a man have a diſeaſe in his body, that he is ſenſible of, if it be but a weaknes or infirmitie, and not a raigning diſeaſe, hee'l be very exact in obſerving the rules of his Phyſitian,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> ſet the moſt luſcious meat before him, if the eating of it ſhould indanger the breking out of his diſeaſe, he will not dare to taſt of it, and hee'l be verie cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, how he miſtimes himſelf, he will have a ſpeciall care not to doe any thing that may give a vent to his trouble.</p>
               <p>It is true notwithſtanding all the care he can take, his trouble will now and then break out, but yet this is no ſuperſedeas to his care, but rather a whetſtone of his diligence. Indeed he that is ſick of a burning feaver, and ſuch like diſeaſes, that have the upperhand of nature, theſe doe make us careleſſe of thoſe things that belong to our health, and cauſe us to pitch upon ſuch things as doe feed our diſeaſe, rather then upon ſuch things as ſtrengthen nature. So here, if thy ſinnes be ſuch as hinder thy exactneſſe, and cauſe thee to make proviſion for thy luſts, they are ſins of preſumption, but if they be ſuch ſinnes as are an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to further thy exactneſſe, and increaſe thy care to walke after the wayes of God: if thou dareſt not neglect thy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in prayer, nor omit any duty, nor walk excen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically to the rule of Gods word, it is but an infirmity, ſuch a ſinne as may very well ſtand and comply with the ſtate of grace.</p>
               <p>It is remarkable, that the infirmities of the Saints have been chiefly diſcovered about thoſe graces for which they have been moſt commended.<note place="margin">☜</note> As <hi>Abraham</hi> is chiefly commended for his faith, yet thoſe infirmities of his recorded in Scripture, as his carnall knowledge of <hi>Hagar,</hi> his equivocating concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116266:13"/> nis wife <hi>Sarah,</hi> were nothing elſe but acts of unbeleefe. So <hi>Iob</hi> is chiefly commended for his patience, yet all his infirmities we can read of were nothing elſe but acts of impatience, what doth this intimate unto us, but that the ſight of their infirmities, have taken advantage to ſtudie the contrary grace ſo much the more, and advanced to ſo high a pitch in the practice of it, that they did deſerve rather to be commended for thoſe graces: then to be condemned for the contrary infirmities. And if it be thus with us, it is a good ſigne. If thou beeſt addicted to pride, and the ſight of it makes thee to ſtrive ſo much the more to be humble, and to attaine to ſo much of humility, that thou deſerveſt to be commended for it, rather then to be condemned for thy pride; Thou ſhalt never ſtand indicted as a preſumptuous ſinner, though thy ſinnes may break out now and then. And the like I may ſay of thy inclination to uncleanneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fiftly and laſtly, The Gibeonites were enemies to the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, and yet carried the matter ſo, that they made them believe that they came from farre. So a ſinne of infirmity is ſo neere grace, that as <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſtrugled both in one wombe, ſo do they conflict and graſple together in one ſoule, yea in one and the ſelf-ſame faculty of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>There is never a ſinne of infirmity but it is confronted by the contrary grace, and that in the ſame ſubject, yet Sathan puts ſuch lies upon theſe ſins of infirmity many times, that they make us believe, that there is a mighty diſtance betwixt us and grace, and to call the truth of our converſion into queſtion: Thus <hi>David</hi> in the 77. <hi>Pſal.</hi> falling into a miſpriſion of his eſtate, and crying out as one that was caſt out of Gods favour,<note place="margin">Simele.</note> in the 20. ver. char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his infirmity with all. Sin though but of infirmity will prove as a Thiefe in our candle, it dimmes our light, and ſteals away our love, neither can I ſee how a conſtant and never inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted aſſurance, may comply with ſuch a meaſure of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116266:13"/> as is yet imperfect, whatever ſome may pretend to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Now ſinnes of preſumption are quite contrary to this, for though they are at a great diſtance from grace, inſomuch that he that is under the Dominion of thoſe ſinnes, cannot juſtly claim the priviledge of a child of God, yet Sathan put ſuch lyes upon theſe ſins, that they make us believe, that true grace &amp; they may very wel ſtand together, according to that of <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 30. <hi>ver.</hi> 12, <hi>There is a generation that is pure in their owne eyes, though they be not cleanſed from their wickedneſſe.</hi> Thus the preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſinner in the 29. of <hi>Deut.</hi> verſe. 19. will needes claime a right in <hi>Garizim</hi> the mountain of bleſſing, when as notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he is bound to make his reſidence in mount <hi>Ebal</hi> the mountain of curſes, <hi>ſpeaking peace to himſelf, when yet he walks in the ſtubborneſſe of his heart,</hi> and the expreſſion which the Holy Ghoſt addes is worth the obſerving, it is ſaid of him that <hi>he addes drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe to thirſt.</hi> That is he doth as a drunkard,<note place="margin">Simele.</note> that is in love with drunkeneſſe and loath to pick a quarrell with it, finding it to be loathſome and overcharging nature, he doth therfore feed upon ſalt meates, that may provok thirſt, that ſo his exceſſe in drinking may be the more pleaſing to his Pallat, and he through the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency of nature may not be drawn to forſake it.</p>
               <p>So a preſumptuous ſinner perſwades himſelf of an intereſt in Chriſts death, not as one that flees thither for refuge, from the fury of the avenger of blood, but as one that is loath to pick a quarrell againſt ſinne, which he knowes is terrible to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and therefore might through the ſting of a ſelf-accuſing ſpirit be imbittered unto him, therefore he is deſirous to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe, that becauſe Chriſt died for ſinners, his ſinnes will breake no ſquare, as if Chriſt did therefore come into the world to make ſinne leſſe dangerous then it was before, and not rather to give us grace to ſubdue ſinnes, and to bring us to a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116266:14"/> greater meaſure of loathing and deteſtation of it, as receiving a greater and more bloody tincture of guilt from his death, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it could have had from the Law. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the differences betwixt ſinnes of infirmity &amp; ſinnes of preſumption, in which as I have eſchewed the one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, which is to ſtrenghten the hands of the wicked, ſo haue I laboured to avoid the other extreame in making the heart of Gods people ſadd, whom the Lord hath not made ſadd.</p>
               <p>Therefore come on you bruiſed reeds and ſmoaking flax, which are ſo oppreſſed with the ſenſe of ſinne, <hi>that you deſpiſe the conſolations of the almighty,</hi> come and view your ſelfe in this glaſſe, and you ſhall ſee what little cauſe you have to bee dejected, it is indeed a bitter thing to ſinne againſt God, but yet ſo long as your ſinnes have not worſe qualities then theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, you have cauſe to lift up your heads and owne your evidences. If your ſinnes be ſo farre kept under, as they are forced to officiate, and help forward the worke of humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If they doe joyn with grace in the deſtruction of other ſinnes (for it is not unuſuall for grace to call out a ſinne of infirmity to perfect mortification.) If they give occaſion to thoſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all victoryes, which diſcover ſo much of the glorious power of God in the ſoule, If they hinder not but rather further our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſſe, and laſtly if they be ſuch neer neighbours to grace, as that grace and they may ſtand together in one ſubject. Comfort thy ſelf whatever the bulk of thy ſin be, thou haſt not yet broke the Covenant, and ſo long as Chriſt is the great Chancellour of Heaven and carryes a Chancery in his boſome, thou ſhalt never take the foyle. Indeed if thy ſinnes beare the Eare-marke of Preſumption, I deare not open this City of refuge unto thee, for God himſelfe hath locked thee out: ſo long thou conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueſt in that condition, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. ver. 19.</p>
               <p>But yet for further ſatisfaction: It will not be amiſſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116266:14"/> what to judge of thoſe enormious ſinnes of the Saints which are upon record, <hi>Lots</hi> inceſt <hi>Davids</hi> adultery and murther and the like, did they not break the Covenant in committing of them. To this I anſwer.</p>
               <p>That to break the Covenant is a ſin unto death, it is a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all adultery, a forſaking of God, that wee may goe a whoring after the Creature, and into ſuch ſinnes the Saints of God cannot fall, becauſe the ſeed of God remains in them, therefore they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thus ſinne unto death.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe theſe ſinnes have a great deale of horror in them, they are Sea-marks from which we muſt flee, as their vertuous actions are land marks, to which we muſt deſire to approach in a way of imitation.</p>
               <p>Nay if any one ſhall ſay that they did lye dead for a time without either the ſenſe or uſe of grace, I will not much gaine ſay him.</p>
               <p>But this I confidently affirm that they were not radically dead, that is they were not ſo dead, but that there was a principle and roote of life left in them. I may compare their condition to Chriſts condition, when he was dead: they will runne parallell in theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>Though Chriſt was dead, yet that Hypoſtatical union betwixt his God-head and Manhood were not diſſolved, but his divine nature was as really united to his man hood at his death as it was when he was alive; now for aſmuch as the God-head is a quickning ſpirit, nay life it ſelf, and the author and giver of life, it muſt needs follow that there was ſtil a root of life left in him, therefore he could not be radically dead. So by thoſe ſinnes which the Saints committed, the myſticall union, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and their ſoules was not diſſolved, whereby he as their head, and they as his members. Impoſſible it is that a man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116266:15"/> thus united unto Chriſt, ſhould be quite caſt of from Chriſt. For then Chriſt himſelfe muſt be maimed by the loſſe of a member.</p>
               <p>See what full deſcription Chriſt himſelfe gives of that union <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. <hi>ver,</hi> 23. I <hi>in them, and thou in me.</hi> where we ſee that this myſticall union is compared to that eſſentiall union which is betwixt him and his father, and therefore as that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſſolved, no more can this. &amp; I am perſwaded that if the Patrons of the Apoſtacy of the Saints had felt the vertue &amp; effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of this union, they would never have broached ſuch an errour. Now foraſmuch as this Chriſt which is in them, and ſo neerely joyned to them is a quickning ſpirit, it is impoſſible that they ſhould ſo fall but that ſtill there is a Root of life left in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though Chriſt dyed, yet he ſaw no corruption, that is he did not rot in his grave. So the Saints though they ſin &amp; ungrievouſly, yet they never go ſo far as to rot in thir ſin, they are never brought ſo low, as that their root ſhould becom <hi>rotteneſſe,</hi> as the Scripture phraſe is. Rottenneſſe ariſeth from hence, when the outward adventicious heat drawes out the inward and radicall moyſture, and makes it runne into the outward parts. So then a man rots away in ſinnne, when the moiſture of his inward mind and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is ſo drawn away from God, as that it is wholly ſet upon outward things. Now a Child of God can never fall thus low. For to be carnally minded is death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. ver. 6. whereas a belever as I proved before cannot ſinne unto death. I thinke no child of God drunk ſo deep of the puddle of Epicuriſme and ſenſuallity as <hi>Salomon</hi> did: yet looke into <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 2. ver. 3. which is his recantation Sermon, and there you ſhall finde him profeſſe, that though he gave himſelfe <hi>to wine, yet he acquainted his heart with wiſdom:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, although I gave my ſelfe to pleaſure yet I reſolved to keepe wiſedome and the feare of God in my heart, and to governe my affaires by the ſame, and to uſe it as a bridle to check me in thoſe abominations.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116266:15"/>
               <p>As the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Judges leave the upper ſeate of judgement empty for God. So <hi>Salomon</hi> when he was at the loweſt ebb, reſerved the higheſt ſeate of his heart and affections for God. Indeed that Seate was empty, it was not adorned with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence as before it was (the more was the pitty) but yet it was reſerved for God, free from the incroachments of earthly vanityes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The death that Chriſt died was the death of the Croſſe, and one reaſon why Chriſt choſe this death, as Divines affirme, was becauſe this death did wound his body, but did not mangle it. So Chriſtians when they fall into ſinnes, their graces are <hi>wounded</hi> but not <hi>mangled,</hi> that is, they are <hi>weakned,</hi> but not-made <hi>uſeleſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A man would have thought that the grace of ſelf-denyal had been wholly deſtroyed in the ſons of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> by that fit of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. vers 23. but yet we finde, it retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its full proportion, though it was wounded by that ſting of that contrary diſtemper, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they fel into, but notwithſtanding when Chriſt cal'd for this grace: It immediatly came forth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to act her part, they expected to ſit at his right hand, &amp; Chriſt asked them, whether they were able to drink of that Cup, that he drunk of, and to be baptized with the baptiſme that he was baptized with. And it appeares by their anſwer, how ready they were to ſtoop to that hot peece of ſervice. They were not ſo ambitious to weare a <hi>Crown:</hi> but they were as wiling to kiſſe the ſtake, not not ſo deſirous to <hi>raign,</hi> as they were wiling to <hi>burn,</hi> which ſhews that though their grace was wounded yet not man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled by their ſinne.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As Chriſt did raiſe himſelfe by his own power. So they were active in their recovery; not meerely paſſive, as they were at their converſion, when there was nothing in them to cloſe with grace, but in this recovery there was ſomthing left in them whereby
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116266:16"/> they were not meere patients, bue agents in their recovery. As <hi>Peter</hi> wept himſelfe alive againe, and <hi>David</hi> repented himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live againe, and <hi>Solomon</hi> preached himſelf alive againe. Thus we ſee what to judg of thoſe groſſe ſinnes of the Saints.</p>
               <p>But ſome men will object and ſay, that this doctrine of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, ſhould be rather extermined then determined in the Pulpit, becauſe it may nouriſh ſpirituall Idleneſſe and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For if men be taught, that having grace, they cannot looſe it, why ſhould they feare to commit any ſinne? And why may they not grow careleſſe, and throw the plough into the hedge to make holy day?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, If true grace will give way to ſuch wantonneſſe: at her perill, conſidering that it is the keeper of every faithful ſoule and not the ſoule the keeper of it, and therefore Chriſtians are ſaid to be under the dominon of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. ſo that no ſuch thing can happen except grace it ſelf ſhould prove ungratious.<note place="margin">Simele.</note> If there were ſuch a fire as could not be quenched, would it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never reſiſt his contrary? So becauſe grace is of that ſtrength as it can never periſh, nor be wholly extinguiſhed, ſhall it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceaſe to reſiſt ſinne? yeas ſure it will reſiſt it not only by counterfightings but by counterluſtings, <hi>Gal</hi> 5.24. The fleſh cannot ſo much as put forth a deſire to ſinne, but the ſpirit will put forth a counter deſire to ſuppreſſe that. It is true, ſometime corruption ſeems to get the advantage in the run, but grace will have the advantage againe in the <hi>turne.</hi> And though a Chriſtian may fall very low, yet we may ſay of that grace, in whoſe cuſtodie he is, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of God himſelf <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.7, 8. <hi>Whether ſhall</hi> I <hi>flie from thy preſence,</hi> &amp;c. So may wee ſay, whether ſhall a Chriſtian flie from ſuch a keeper. If to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven I am ſure we cannot then flie from it, for thither is grace bound, and it hath a Commiſſion to bring us thither. If to hell grace will find us out there too, and be ſure to bring us back. If
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116266:16"/> we ſhould ſtraggle and ſtray and have our heart too far carried away from God this grace ſhall lead us to God againe, and <hi>her right hand ſhall hold us up.</hi> If darkeneſſe of deſertion cover us, grace will help us at a dead lift, and <hi>turn our darkneſſe into light.</hi> And by this it appeares that the doctrine of perſeverances gives no way to licentiouſnes and carnall libertie.</p>
               <p>And whereas the patrons of the Apoſtacie of the Saints charge this doctrin with this inconvenience, that it opens a door to ſpirituall idleneſſe and ſecurity, this imputation may iuſtly be retorted upon them. For you know a Chriſtian hath much adoe to get grace, it will coſt him hot water, many heart breaking and bitter pangs, before Ieſus Chriſt be framed and faſhioned in him: Now if people be taught, that men have no ſooner gotten grace, but they are in danger to looſe it again: will not this enervate and emaſculate end overthrow all godly endeavours? What heart can a man have to take any great pains for that, and to be at a great charge to purchaſe that, which he is not ſure to hold? In all conveyances there is a <hi>tenendum,</hi> as well as an <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum,</hi> it is conveyed to us, not only to <hi>have</hi> but to <hi>hold,</hi> elſe we would hardly lay out any money about ſuch purchaſe. So take away perpetuity and perſeverance from grace, and what heart can we have to take any paines about it? This is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience that will follow from this error.</p>
               <p>Beſides this opinion is moſt uncomfortable, for it keeps the people in perpetuall ſuſpence: It makes the graces of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to be like Marchants goods that hang upon rops, even upon the ſandic ropes of our weak and frail endeavours. And whereas Chriſt hath made an exceeding rich will, yet it ſeems by this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that he hath made it ſo looſe, that no man can certainly prove the will, nor be aſſured, whether the will belong to him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116266:17"/> or no. Again how can grace that may be <hi>mortall,</hi> ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort an <hi>immortall</hi> ſoule. At leaſt by this doctrine we cannot be ſoundly comforted till we have perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which cannot be till after death, at which time men ſhall be either above or beneath comfort. Thus much for this uſe.</p>
               <p>Other uſes were omitted for want of time, but ſhall be added if this finde acceptance, wherein I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſcover the nature of Apoſtacy, which ſinne ſeemes now to be calculated for the <hi>Meridian</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Imprimatur, <hi>Edmond Calamy.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
